Hey, hey,
hey, hey.
Good morning everyone and welcome to the
Fiber Broadband Association's five for
breakfast. We're now in our sixth
episode of 2026 and our gold sponsor for
five breakfast is conducts. Before I'd
like to start, I'd like to give a big
shout out to our good friend Mike
Romano, who has been recently named the
CEO of NTCA to succeed retiring Shirley
Bloomfield. Both Shirley and Mike are
the absolute finest leaders in our
industry and Shirley be greatly missed.
And we could not be more excited for
Mike in his new role. So
congratulations, Mike. In Washington
this week, the House and Senate are in
session and notably funding for the
Homeland um for Homeland Security
expires on Friday. Yesterday, Senator,
excuse me, Secretary Lednik testified
before the Senate Appropriations
Committee on Commerce, Justice, Science,
and Related Agencies regarding broadband
deployment funding at Department of
Commerce. FBA and its members have
raised concerns about the proposed low
Earth orbit rider contract provisions
that can materially altered the
foundation or the uh foundation
performance oversight and accountability
standards under the B program. During
the hearing, Secretary Ludnik confirmed
that the proposed rider is rejected as
it falls outside both NI's guidelines
and the statute and the states are well
within their authority to pursue
alternative execution options. So what
that means if uh the LEO guys aren't
able to meet the performance
requirements then uh they'll the states
will move to some other technology. We
appreciate Senate uh secretaries Lnik
and NI's leadership and guidance as the
states implement this complex program.
State broadband officers must fully be
fully empowered to enforce u be
requirements and reject contract
provisions that undermine transparency
oversight and accountability. We're also
pleased to report that NTI has now
approved final proposals for 50 of the
56 states and territories. As a
reminder, NTI will be holding a
listening session today on the remaining
bead funds starting at 2, excuse me, 2
p.m. Eastern. You know, last week, uh,
the Fire Broadband Association held its
first regional fiberconnect workshop of
2026 in Oklahoma City. We're focused on
tribal, and it was the biggest regional
that we've had to date. Um, so it was
amazing and we are very appreciative of
the Oklahoma Speaker of the House Kyle
Hilbert, his thoughtful key keynote
address and for meeting with our
members. Also, Judge Bill Grall um at
SBA held a roundt discussion with our
Oklahoma members to identify business
challenges that he could share with
President Trump. Our next regional
fiberconnect workshop will be held in
Indianapolis on Thursday, March 19th.
You can go to our website to register.
And as a reminder, uh the FBA will be
holding its second annual public policy
summit and flyin in DC on February 24th
and 25th, bringing members together with
congressional leaders, emission
administration officials, and a federal
agency stakeholders to focus on how we
can bring high-speed reliable
connectivity to all. So last week on
Fire for Breakfast, our guest was our
good friend Assad Ramzali who is the
director of artificial intelligence and
technology policy at Vanderbelt Policy
Accelerator. He discussed AI chips in
the battle for network innovation and he
shared with us the advances in
artificial intelligence, provided some
insights on AI related policy challenges
and what to watch for. So if you missed
last week's session, you can go to our
website and watch the replay. Today on
Fire for Breakfast, our guest is Dr. Dr.
Tamara Holmes, the director of the
office of broadband at DHCD, provide an
update on Virginia's fiber projects and
initiatives. Dr. Holmes is the director
for the office of broadband at DHCD and
has been in that role since September
2019.
She has spent over 20 years in public
sector in the field of community and
economic development in New York, New
Jersey, and Chesterfield, Virginia. Dr.
Holmes has played a instrumental role in
the creation of Virginia's
telecommunications initiative VAT
and is leading the development of the
program that has grown from a million
dollars to $750 million in
appropriations since 2017. She's
responsible for coordinating the efforts
across the Commonwealth to invest an
additional 1.48 billion in fence from
the bipartisan infrastructure law
allocated to close the digital divide in
Virginia by 2029.
Prior in her current role, she was the
associate director for policy and
strategic development office in the
community development division at DHCD.
In addition, as serving broadband
director, she serves as the regional or
the Virginia Appalachin Regional
Commission, ARC, program manager
overseeing ARC's economic and community
development program in 25 counties and
eight independent cities in the
Appalachin region. She holds a master's
degrees in urban planning analysis with
a concentration in housing community
development. She received her doctorate
in public policy administration from
VCU. So, welcome Dr. Holmes. And for
audience, please type in the questions
as we go and I'd like to get started.
So, Dr. Holmes, uh, a little bit of a
rough start, but I'm glad that you made
it. Um, so how have you been doing?
>> Good morning. Thank you Gary and team
for having me join you at Fiber
Broadband Association this morning. Um
things have been going well in the
Commonwealth of Virginia.
>> So you know when we we were last I
wouldn't say last together but we had uh
one of our regional events in Richmond
and it was prior to you know right when
um we were getting ready to have final
proposals and Virginia was in the lead.
You had Louisiana then was going to be
Virginia's. So what all happened? What
was all the thing that hung kind of hung
you guys up from being the leaders?
>> Uh, so I've been saying the broadband
equity access and deployment program is
the longest program I actually hadn't
started in my career yet. Um, and so
depending on what point in time I feel
like if you ever um I don't know if you
you you remember like there's a movie it
talks about like things just happening
over and over again. And so I feel like
with the B program um it's it's been a
long time coming. And so, um, we were
actually in disagreement over what we
considered, um, at the time perceived as
rate regulation. And so, we kind of went
back and forth with the leadership at
NCIA at the time regarding that. And
then eventually we finally um were able
to negotiate something and get our um
final proposal um to go through the
process for approval.
>> Well, great. Hey. Um, so today, you
know, NCIA is having their, uh,
listening session and, um, what do you,
you know, so Ariel has, or excuse me,
Assistant Secretary Roth has been, uh,
telegraphing that, you know, they're
certainly interested in investing in um,
streamlining um, permitting, permitting
reform. There's a number of other
things. How is permitting in the state
of uh, Virginia?
So, just to give you a little bit of
history about um broadband in Virginia,
I know you talked a little bit about the
the body program. It's the Virginia
Telecommunication Initiative. And so, we
started investing as a state in
broadband in 2017. And so, it was the
million-dollar program as you said, and
I often goes 1 million, 1 million, 5
million, 19 million, 50 million, and
then 750 million. And so in 2022, we
were allocated $750 million which
included general state general fund
dollars, American rescue plan, and also
capital project fund. So we ended up
going from a a state appropriated
program to a state appropriation along
with two different distinct um federal
resources as part of our our funding
opportunities in the Commonwealth. And
so I jokingly say when you take $750
million and you put it out for grant
awards, we jokingly I jokingly say we
broke every possible system that it
takes to start getting broadband to
communities. And so that's where
preventing comes into place. And so we
um have gotten a lot of bumps and
bruises over the last um four years of
doing um investments through the ARPA
and CPF funding because it was such a
huge investment. Um again, we went from
um a $19 million program in in 2020 to a
$50 million program in 21 to 750
million. And so everything that could
possibly happen and be a challenge to
get broadband to um residents across the
Commonwealth happened. Um, we had to
have discussions with our pole owners
regarding access to the polls. Um, we
had I I will say the word railroad, but
if you all can do your own research on
how that worked out for us there um as a
state and then also our utility
location. So, I jokingly say we broke
every possible system it takes to get
broadband to to folks homes. And so we
have been working closely with all of
our partners across the Commonwealth to
get to those um connections that were
awarded through that significant
investment in 2022. And so when I hear
permitting, I'm like, I hope that other
states are prepared because the
challenges that we experienced, um I
think I feel like we're in a better
place today than we were four years ago
around permitting. Uh we have a great
relationship with our Virginia
Department of Transportation. and we're
actually partnering with them on our RV
program. We have a great relationship
with our Virginia 811 folks. That's our
utility locate organization.
Um we have a better relationship with um
American Railroad Association. Their
Virginia folks have been key partners in
trying to get um railroad crossings um
done. And so I feel like we are again in
a way better place than we were when we
first started with the huge increase in
funding in 2022. And so we're prepared.
>> Well, everybody likes to be upset with
the Department of Transportation or the
railroads, you know, just uh thinking
they're making life difficult, but their
number one obligation is roadway safety
and and rail safety. And
>> you know, railroads are very very
dangerous places and you know, as as
well as highways, you know, and people
can get killed very easily. So just
having trucks and things and uh people
doing work, it's a big deal. So it's uh
it's very disruptive but there is
>> you know we provided some path for um
suggestions on how to move forward and
hopefully uh NI will take us up on some
of our suggestions. uh one of the
questions that came in so you know we've
we had the whole benefit of the bargain
deal um which freed up $20 billion uh
but one of the things that uh one of the
questions came in with the overturning
of the digital equity act is there any
light at the end of the tunnel with DOP
grants
>> so we don't know yet what NCIA will
allow for the eligible uses for the
non-eployment and so just so you all
know if you haven't paid attention in
Virginia. So, we did um finalize and
received our approval from NIA for $545
million of our $1.48 billion allocation.
And so, that leaves about $800 million
um available for for B non-deployment.
And so, we are currently awaiting
guidance from NCIA on eligible uses of
those funds. And so, um, I won't say
that we'll,
you know, we're not quite sure what NDI
will allow us to use the funds for. And
so, we are in communications, we have
been in communications with all of the
entities that have submitted
applications through our digital equity
act program that was ultimately canled.
And so um we will have to stay tuned to
see what our opportunity will be of
being able to utilize um the B
non-deployment funding for those
potential projects that came in. We're
just not quite we're not sure what we
will be allowed to do yet.
>> And since you know the Virginia
Telecommunications Initiative's been
around for a long time now, nine years,
you've had a number of different
programs, state funding, ARPA, C uh
capital projects funds, you know,
reconnect, all this stuff. What so what
what progress have you guys done with
all this different funding and and what
what has been the easiest program to
administer?
So what's been interesting about the
work in Virginia and so we we actually
had a I call it the big brother to the
body program Gary we had Vatipi and it's
funny it's one of the first acronyms I
ever made in state government and so we
had the Virginia Telecommunication
Planning Initiative and that was
actually in 2016 and so we worked with
several communities across the
Commonwealth that were interested in you
know addressing the the lack of
broadband in their communities and so a
lot of those communities ended up coming
in for funding over the last nine years
that we have had the body program. And
so we've had great success um across the
Commonwealth with communities getting to
universal connectivity. Um and so we
actually got to 200,000 locations as of
December 31st of 2025 of the locations
that were awarded in 2021 and 2022. Um
and so we're about almost 90% of
Virginia currently has access to
broadband and um several of the prop
several of the the locations that are
not currently um built out are either
currently being built and underway
through our investments through body or
are waiting for us to get the projects
under contract for bead. So, we're about
almost 90% um across the Commonwealth
and um we do have um trying to think
what I was going to say. We do have some
um sorry, I lost my thought for a
second. And so, we do have projects um
all across the Commonwealth and we have
some communities that are reaching
almost 90% coverage individually if you
start looking at them county by county.
>> And what what which program has been the
easiest to administer?
H. So, well, I mean, I like to say my
state program because we get to build
the rules around that. Um, and so we um
and so, like I said, the the allocation
that we received in 2022 was $50 million
in state money. And so, I would always
say the state money has been the easiest
because the body program was created in
budget language. I don't know how much
you know about um how a bill becomes a
law and a budget gets appropriated in
government but um we were able to
develop the program guidelines in
partnership with our stakeholders across
the commonwealth with local governments
with internet service providers with
their um association leadership and so
we really have a public private
partnership within the commonwealth in
our broadband efforts and so that's what
I think has contributed to our success
so I would say our state program has
been the easiest program. Um, Treasury
has been good good as well. Um, and so
we'll see how it goes with NCIA. That'll
be my first time working with them on a
deployment program.
>> Well, good. Um, one of the questions we
had from registrance is what's the uh
the ETA or schedule for fiber
connectivity in the southern or
southside Virginia region?
>> Southern or southside Virginia. So, we
do have um some projects in southern
southside Virginia. Um, and so I will
give you, we do have a publicly facing
dashboard. And what I'll do, Gary, is
share that link for your, um, attendees
to know where to go. We actually have a
map that gives real-time updates on how
the projects are progressing by award
across the state. And so, um, a good
chunk of southern Virginia and southside
Virginia were awarded in 2022. There are
some locations that are part of the BE
program that were awarded um to Empower
who's a company um that builds in
Southside and South V um Southside
excuse me in southern Virginia.
So, you know, I was talking to Venice
the other day from Louisiana and he said
with the combinations of all his
programs, they are going to be at 99%
fiber across the state despite, you
know, kind of being beaten back a little
bit on the bead program on their fiber.
Um, how are you guys doing with all the
combinations of all your programs? You
know, how as far as fiber deployment,
>> I h I haven't run the numbers on where
we're going to be in terms of tech. uh
we are tech neutral in the Commonwealth.
And so even our our state funded
projects have been techneutral. We
funded and I'll give you a great example
of a county um um Rono County, they they
came in with cable, fiber, and a fixed
wireless provider on a body award in
2022. And that's going to get that
county over 90%. And so I know I'm on a
podcast with you. Um, and so I don't
have an exact breakdown of where we're
at in terms of fiber coverage across the
state, but we're tech neutral in
Virginia. And so because our program,
the body program, actually runs through
local governments and units of local
government, we defer to them to identify
what technology they think um would best
serve their community. Of course, um, if
you're familiar if you're not familiar
with Virginia's terrain, we have terrain
that's, you know, from the the the
mountains of Southwest Virginia all the
way to the Eastern Shore. So our terrain
is wide and vast and so it will take
different technologies to get to to
every unserved location across the
state. And so I don't have the exact
breakdown by technology in terms of
coverage. I know that more than 90% of
our investments um over the last nine
years through the body program have been
primarily Fiverr, but I'd have to
actually run the numbers on actual
coverage to date.
>> All right. So tell us a little bit about
your 2029 goal. What's what's that? How
do you know when you've reached that
goal? of the key metrics.
>> Well, of course, we um track location
based data. Um I I think the best story
the the the one of the things that I
think has made us be successful again is
our partnerships with local governments
and our units of local government. And
so what success to me is hearing from
residents and communities across the
Commonwealth. You know, while we track
metrics, I think metrics are great and
we have the data on where we are in
terms of total coverage across the
state. is really the stories and the
families that whose lives have been
changed through changed through having
access to broadband. Um I'm more of a
qualitative person and so being able to
hear from families and community leaders
about the impact broadband has on on
their famil family's lives um to me is
the best way to learn about our impact
across the state.
>> All right. Well, thank one of the notes
that came across here from Tyler is that
the listening session with NTIA on
nonbeat is is actually from 2 to 4
Eastern. So, um, someone gave me the
wrong notes, but I just looked it up
just to confirm. So, yeah, I'll be 2 to
4 today. And, uh, yeah, my I'm not going
to be able to make that, but my team
will be on that call as well. So, um,
anything that from that call, um, are
you expecting or hoping that people will
bring up?
Um, I I'm going to be listening to hear
because I know it'll be a diverse um
group of stakeholders that'll be on that
call and so I'm more going to be
listening to hear what um because I I
think some of our Virginia partners are
going to join the call today and share
their thoughts and so I'm going to be
more listening about what they'd like to
see the state invest um the beat
non-employment funding in and so looking
forward to hearing those um that input
from them.
So, you know, I mentioned this whole
uh Starlink rider.
Do do you guys come across that much
where um you someone will win an award
and then they'll come and try to change
the rules that violate the statute and
the rules of the program?
>> Well, remember I've been running a state
program. Yeah. Well, I've been running a
state program and so um not in the nine
years I've done a program, I've had um
so So remember B is different from our
state program. My state program, my
contract is with a government entity and
then the government entity has a
different contract with their internet
prov partner that has been awarded the
grant and partnership with the locality.
And so I I do not um we are not I I have
a PhD. I do not have a JD. And so we do
not weigh in on those agreements between
our government entities who are our
grantees and their internet providers.
And so bead is going to be the first
time the Commonwealth will directly
contract with internet service
providers. And so I know other states um
directly contract with internet
providers. We do not in our in our
normal allocation and of course be
changes that. And so I will tell you
even in the early days of the the body
program I've we do share our contract
with the governments and they do share
the contract with a lot of their ISP
partners. And so I will say I've um not
been shocked by getting having um
attorneys from internet companies often
want us to revise our contract that they
are not actually a party to. But a lot
of times localities will pass on some of
those requirements very much similar to
what NCI is going to do with us where
they're going to pass requirements on to
us that we'll pass the ISPs. Same thing
in the body program. And so I will say
that I have um had a lot of phone calls
with attorneys from some some internet
companies over the years that have tried
to rewrite our state contract. Um and
the good thing is that we often can
figure out because we don't customize
our contracts by project. um we have
standard language and so had to stand my
ground a couple of times with um
attorneys from internet companies and so
but it's always worked itself out and so
um
>> we were yeah we were thrilled that the
secretary held the ground on that
because it just would unravel everything
you know with between that and Amazon
Leo you know asking for extensions on
you know delays to their deployments so
you know well I had Brandy Raider on
here a couple weeks ago from Colorado
broadband office and they initially had
a 70% fiber and then after the benefit
of the bargain they ended up with 51%
LEO. Uh and she was describing how you
know takes LEO has four years to build
which is kind of crazy because they're
already supposed to be in the sky and
then there's 10 years of meeting the the
minimums you know 100 by 20. So
basically it's going to be 14 years to
know whether you actually got the
performance promise. Is that are you
guys running into any kind of concerns
like that where you know critical areas
that are very remote are going to be
stuck with waiting till 2040 to know
whether they really got their 100 by 20.
>> And so for us I don't I'll share with
you Gary I don't know if you know our
breakdown in terms of the technology
awarded through our bead program. And so
I'll kind of share that first before I
answer the question. And so for
Virginia, um 80% of our locations are
going to get fiber, 1% will get fixed
wireless, 6% will get hybrid coax cable,
and then 13% will get satellite. And so
for us, I do know that there's some
conversations regarding um Kyper and and
and
Starlink. And so we do have both
companies that have been awarded
locations in Virginia. And so they're
currently in their pre-contract phase.
And so we are having conversations with
um both of them regarding what we just
recently learned regarding the writer as
well as the the time the timeline
extension for hyper. And so we will most
likely as you said earlier defer to NCIA
because that those are changes that are
um being requested across the board for
all the awards across the country. And
so I'm going to defer to NCIA to provide
us guidance on how they want us to deal
with those because we do have to man
manage expectations. I will tell you
running a program for the last nine
years when folks hear about money being
awarded and them getting internet they
want internet today. And so we have um
done a good job I would say of managing
expectations but with the B program
we'll have to do a better job of manage
managing expectations because at least
with the body program there's a
government in between us who of you know
those community leaders live in their
their communities they see each other at
Walmart their local grocery stores their
baseball games and so we we often
partner on communications and so B will
be slightly different for us and so I'm
going to defer to NCIA on how they want
us to deal with the the rider
um that all the states received and also
regarding the extension for Kyper.
So now as you're you know you'll be able
to get everybody connected by you know
2029 which is awesome but AI is kind of
been taking over the world right or as
they say eating the world and you know
what we've seen from their studies is
that you know AI the the subscribers use
of AI is highly dependent on the quality
of connections where 75% of the
subscribers on fi on fiber use AI uh
daily or less than 10% on satellite and
it kind of goes, you know, down between
there with cable and so forth. How are
you guys looking at your broadband
office at looking at um AI and you know
how how you're constructing your
networks and kind of what the future of
what you're going to be doing, you know,
beyond broadband to make sure that
everybody in Virginia is able to
participate in the AI future.
And so I I to so the funny thing is
someone told me that you know the
internet runs through Virginia. That's
like the thing we know, right? And so um
we've done I I went through a Virginia
executive leadership program. And so
that was probably the most I've ever
learned about our project was on
artificial intelligence. And so I
learned a lot about kind of where we are
as a as a commonwealth. And so one of
the stats which I I'll repeat, but I
can't remember the source. And then I
also have to question if it's reliable.
And so it talked about like what
percentage of Virginia like we're ninth
or something in the use of AI as a
state. Again, I I was told that that
source may not be reliable, so don't
quote me on that. Um and and so I think
part of the work that's important for us
is making sure that one my ultimate goal
is to make sure everyone has access to
broadband. as the first that is the
first and foremost goal I am responsible
for doing as the director of the office
of broadband um and how we get everyone
connected of course is through a
diversity of technology and so we do in
our body program and will require as
part of our B program of course be will
require speed testing we actually
require that for our state program Gary
so the investments that are that have
been made in Virginia and that are
currently being made across the state
currently under construction they do
have to do speed tests we get
information on at the residents level um
on how the the service is performing.
And so
we want to make sure that we are
preparing Virginiaians for not just
their technology needs for today, but
their technology needs for the future.
And so we are doing the best we can in
our due diligence to make sure that
happens across the state. And if it
includes, you know, making sure families
have access to, you know, high speeded
reliable internet to to be able to um
utilize AI, that's the goal that we
have.
>> One of the questions that came in is um
do any of your awards include a
provision to offer broadband or internet
education or training to unserved or
underserved communities?
>> So through the body program, as I said
earlier, those contracts are with local
governments. And so some local
governments do put because remember I
said they have a contract with the
internet provider. Some local
governments have put different
provisions within their contracts with
the internet providers on what they'd
like to see. Um one of our um ideas that
actually we we u we call it research and
development. It's really rip off and
duplicate. And I don't know how much you
know about um electric utility. So we
have a lot of um our electric utility
electric cooperatives that um also now
have broadband subsidiaries in Virginia.
And so they have something that they um
provide education on. It's called the
cooperative living room. And um the
concept actually comes um started with
the invent um electricity going into
rural communities where they would have
like a makeshift house and they would
show families how do you use because in
the early years of electricity they also
had to convince people to take the
service. And so what the electric
cooperatives tell me is that they were
able to show families like how to use
electricity within their home. And so
one of our cooperative partners, um,
Ruleban,
um, had a cooperative living room in one
of the counties that they're doing a
body project in at the community center.
And so it's literally a makeshift, it's
a room. And so they have like a living
room section and a a TV room and a kids
room. And shows how you can use smart
technology within your home once you
have access to broadband. And so one of
the ideas, you know, we had early on um
to utilize which is public information
for our now canceled digital equity
grant was to replicate that regionally
across the state. And so um some of our
communities as and so I bring up that
example. So Denwitty in their project
with rural band had that as one of their
requirements because they wanted to make
sure that their families were educated.
And so we do see innovation uh
innovative ideas across the Commonwealth
on how communities want to see their
residents become educated around
broadband access. And so the cooperative
living room was a great example in
Denwit County and they've replicated it
um in a couple other places. And so we
were going to try to actually replicate
it regionally with our digital equity
grant but that funding has since been
cancelled.
>> Well, Dr. homes. We just really
appreciate everything you've done for
Virginia and across the nation and your
leadership of the broadband office and
uh we know that uh we appreciate you
guys hanging in there and and keeping
your nose the grindtor as uh the sands
shift beneath you. So, thank you for
that and I want to thank everybody for
joining us today and look forward to get
back to get there next Wednesday with
Michael Thomas of Network Connects who's
going to discuss the hidden
infrastructure behind AI and hypers
scale networks. You're not going to want
to miss that. So, thanks everyone for
joining us. Thank you Dr. Holmes and
look forward to seeing your further
success.
>> Thank you.